A Finding Aid to the Paul Vanderbilt Papers, 1854-1992, bulk 1945-1992, in the Archives of American Art AAA.vandpaul
Archives of American Art
Paul Vanderbilt papers
bulk 1945-1992
1854-1992
AAA.vandpaul
Archives of American Art
26.2 Linear feet
The papers of librarian, curator, and photographer Paul Vanderbilt (1905-1992) measure 26.2 linear feet and date from 1854 to 1992 with the bulk of the material dating from 1945 to 1992. The papers are comprised of biographical materials, personal and business correspondence, interviews, writings and notes, fourteen diaries and two diary fragments, reference and project files, photographic materials, sound recordings, and professional files.
Vanderbilt, Paul
Related Archival Materials note
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Paul Vanderbilt conducted by Richard Doud on November 10, 1964.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1981 by Paul Vanderbilt and in 1993 by his estate through John W. Winn, executor.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of librarian, curator, and photographer Paul Vanderbilt (1905-1992) measure 26.2 linear feet and date from 1854 to 1992 with the bulk of the material dating from 1945 to 1992. The papers are comprised of biographical materials, personal and business correspondence, interviews, writings and notes, fourteen diaries and two diary fragments, reference and project files, photographic materials, sound recordings, and professional files.
Biographical materials include seven appointment books, family letters and documents, and an honorary degree from the University of Wisconsin.
Vanderbilt's correspondence is with colleagues, and organizations including Dorothea Lange, Beaumont Newhall, Roy Stryker, and Julia Vanderbilt.
Sound recordings of interviews of Vanderbilt conducted by Mary North Allen, Barbara Crane, Carl Haywood, Jack Holzhueter, and Jane Plunkett. Other recordings are of Vanderbilt discussing his personal and professional life.
Writings by Paul Vanderbilt include drafts of Between the Landscape and its Other, poems, lectures, student papers, and notes on a variety of subjects. Writings by others are found for William Blake, Gregory Conniff, Woody Guthrie, Michael Lesy, Arnold R. Pilling, Jesse H. Shera, and Roy Stryker.
Fourteen of Vanderbilt's personal diaries and two diary fragments date from 1926 to 1990.
Reference files consist of printed materials on art, art historians, book reviews, library and information studies, photography and microphotography techniques, and other themes of interest to Vanderbilt. Project files include material from Vanderbilt's various projects including a guide to the iconography of Iran, the reclassification of FSA photographs, and the Union Library Catalog of Philadelphia.
Included in professional files are administrative records, correspondence, exhibition files, project files, printed material, and research files created during Vanderbilt's career at the Library of Congress, Graphic History Society, State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Philadelphia Museum of Art, and the Farm Security Administration. Also found are materials for Vanderbilt's work as a consultant for several organizations, lecture documents, and art-related workshops.
Photographs are by and of Paul Vanderbilt, the staff of the Library of Congress, and George Talbot. Negatives include images for the Farm Security Administration. Bibliography cards and photographs of artwork from the Library of Congress can be found on microfilm reels within the collection.
Also found are fourteen unidentified sound recordings.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 10 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1894-1992 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1933-1992 (1.5 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Interviews, 1967-1992 (1.5 linear feet; Box 2-4)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1887-1992 (4.0 linear feet; Box 4-8)
Series 5: Diaries, 1926-1990 (0.5 linear feet; Box 8)
Series 6: Reference Files, 1877-1992 (2.5 linear feet; Box 8-10, 26)
Series 7: Project Files, 1935-1990 (3.0 linear feet; Box 10-13)
Series 8: Professional Files, 1854-1991 (11.7 linear feet; Box 13-24)
Series 9: Photographic Materials, 1912-1980s (0.5 linear feet; Box 24)
Series 10: Sound Recordings, circa 1980s (0.5 linear feet; Box 24-25)
Biographical/Historical note
Paul Vanderbilt (1905-1992) was a librarian, curator, and photographer active in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Washington, D.C. and Madison, Wisconsin.
Paul Vanderbilt was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts and educated in Germany, Switzerland, and Massachusetts. He attended Amherst College from 1923 to 1925 before transferring to Harvard where he graduated with a BA in art history in 1927. After graduation, Vanderbilt traveled to Europe where he studied at the American School of Librarianship in Paris and the Institut de Psychologie Bibliogique in Lausanne. In 1929, he returned to the United States and became a librarian at the Philadelphia Museum of Art and director of the Union Library Catalog project for the Philadelphia area.
In 1941 Vanderbilt began working under Roy Stryker cataloging the extensive photographic survey collection of the Farm Security Administration and U.S. Office of War Information. The collection is a rich resource of images of American life between 1935 and 1944. In 1943, the FSA photograph collection was transferred to the Library of Congress and Vanderbilt went with it as the curator of the newly formed Prints and Photographs Division, eventually becoming the Division chief of fine arts.
During the early 1950s, Vanderbilt also served as the director of the Graphic History Society of America. There he published a quarterly bulletin Eye to Eye and developed a guide to iconography in Iran. In 1954, he became the Curator of Iconographic Collections at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin and worked there until he retired in 1972.
Vanderbilt remained active after retirement. He became an artist-in-residence at the Apeiron Workshops, worked as a photographer for the Seagram courthouse project and the George Eastman House, and was a presenter at multiple conferences. Vanderbilt devoted much of his later life to working on his book titled Between the Landscape and its Other which was published posthumously after Vanderbilt's death in 1992.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Some of the sound recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and digital copies are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Allen, Mary North; Blake, William; Conniff, Gregory, 1944-; Crane, Barbara, d1928-; Graphic History Society of America.; Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967; Haywood, Carl; Holzhueter, Jack; Lange, Dorothea; Lesy, Michael, 1945-; Library of Congress. Prints and Photographs Division.; Newhall, Beaumont, 1908-1993; Philadelphia Museum of Art.; Pilling, Arnold R.; Plunkett, Jane; Shera, Jesse Hauk, 1903-1982; State Historical Society of Wisconsin. Division of Archives and Manuscripts.; Stryker, Roy Emerson, 1893-1975; Talbot, George; Union Library Catalogue of the Philadelphia Metropolitan Area.; United States. Farm Security Administration. Historical Section.; Vanderbilt, Julia; Art historians--United States; Curators--United States; Diaries; Documentary photography--United States; Graphic arts--Historiography; Graphic arts--Iran; Interviews; Librarians; Photographers; Photographs; Photography; Photomicrography; Sound recordings
- Biographical Materials, 1894-1992; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials document Vanderbilt's personal life and family history. Included are seven appointment books, his diploma from Harvard University, letters of his mother and grandmother, his mother's handwritten manual used for teaching at the New York School of Expression, documents pertaining to an honorary degree from the University of Wisconsin along with letters of recommendation that speak to Vanderbilt's character and professional accomplishments, and a photocopy of his suicide notes.
  - General, 1928-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Books, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Books, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appointment Books, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diploma and Report Cards, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family Background, 1900-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family Legal Documents, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family Letters, 1894-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Handwriting Analysis Report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Honorary Degree from University of Wisconsin, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Honorary Degree from University of Wisconsin, Letters of Recommendation, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photocopy of Suicide Notes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minnie Miner Vanderbilt, Manual for New York School of Expression, circa 1898-1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Names and Addresses, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1933-1992; Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  General correspondence is with individuals, organizations, and businesses. Notable correspondents include Lisa Ebright, Dorthea Lange, Beaumont Newhall, Roy Stryker, and Julia Vanderbilt.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by surname or organization name.
  - A, 1958-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Heritage, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Archives of American Art, 1968-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - B, 1939-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bird, Lance, Regarding Film, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bostrom, Roald, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - C, 1973-1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Campion, Eleanor, Nebraska Union Catalog, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Center for Creative Photography at University of Arizona, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Christensen, John, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - D, 1942-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - David R. Godine Publisher, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Designer Decorator News, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - E-F, 1973-1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ebright, Lisa, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Edward Weston's 100th Anniversary, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Employment, 1945-1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - G-H, 1944-1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gallery, Possible Exhibit, circa 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gamma Photo Labs, Inc., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - George Eastman House, 1954-1980 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - The Great Lakes Review, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - I-J, 1954-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Society for General Semantics, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - K-L, 1942-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lambert, Marion, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lange, Dorothea, 1957-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lesy, Michael, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Louisville, University of, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - M, 1942-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McGrath, Frank and Melba, 1972-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Middleton, Wisconsin, 1954-1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Milwaukee Art Center, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Museum of Modern Art, Art Loan, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - N, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Newhall, Beaumont, 1933-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - O-Q, 1936-1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photography, 1938-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - R, 1938-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rhem, James, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - S, 1937-1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Snider, Robert, 1971-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Society for Photographic Education, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Society of Photographic Education Conference in Green Bay, Wisconsin, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Stryker, Roy, 1945-1964 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - T-V, 1935-1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Tate, Vernon, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Vanderbilt, Julia, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Weinstein-Booth Book, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Williams College Center for Environmental Studies, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Wisconsin Academy, 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Wisconsin, University of, 1957-1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - W-Z, 1943-1992 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Interviews, 1967-1992; Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  Thirty-four sound reels and twenty-seven sound cassettes include interviews of and discussions with Paul Vanderbilt about his career, theories on art, and personal life, some of which were conducted by interviewer Jack Holzhueter. Also found among the recordings are conversations with Barbara Crane discussing magic-calligraphy and Paul Strand, with L. Koch discussing self expression, and with Jane Plunkett.
  - Conversation Between Mary North Allen and Carl Haywood, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Conversations Between Paul Vanderbilt and Jack Holzhueter, 1967-1977; 6 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
  - Conversations Between Paul Vanderbilt and Jack Holzhueter, 1967-1977; 4 sound tape reels (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Conversations Between Paul Vanderbilt and Jack Holzhueter, 1977; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Paul Vanderbilt and Barbara Crane Discussing Magic-Calligraphy, 1978; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Paul Vanderbilt and Barbara Crane Discussing Paul Strand, circa 1970; 3 sound tape reels (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Paul Vanderbilt Discussing Life and Career, circa 1970; 21 sound tape reels (Box 3, Folder 7-17)
  - Paul Vanderbilt and Jane Plunkett, 1983; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paul Vanderbilt and "JP", circa 1980s; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Paul Vanderbilt and L. Koch on Self-Expression, circa 1980s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Paul Vanderbilt Discussing Various Subjects, circa 1980s; 15 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 4-8)
  - Notes for Sound Recordings, circa 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Writings and Notes, 1887-1992; Series 4; 4 Linear feet Boxes 4-8
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries
  4.1: Writings by Paul Vanderbilt, 1925-1992
  4.2: Writings by Others, circa 1930s-1990
  4.3: Notes, 1887-1992
  Writings and notes include the manuscript and notes for Vanderbilt's posthumously published book Between the Landscape and its Other, texts for lectures and speeches, and published and unpublished writings by Vanderbilt. Writings by others include student papers and articles about Vanderbilt; a six page autobiographical typescript by Woody Guthrie describing his youth in Oklahoma (probably written in the late 1930s); and additional writings by Michael Lesy, Roy Stryker, Gregory Conniff, Jesses H. Shera, and Arnold R. Pilling. Also found here are extensive notes by Vanderbilt on various topics.
  - Writings by Paul Vanderbilt, 1925-1992; 4.1
    - Afterimage, 1957-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "The Arnold Genthe Collection", Article in The Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Article for The Massachusetts Review, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Drafts, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Final Editorial Work, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Handwritten Draft, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 4, Folder 17-20)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Images, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1988-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Out Takes from Original Manuscript, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Quotations, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Revision Notes, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Unabridged, circa 1989; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Between the Landscape and its Other, Working Copy, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - Book Reviews, 1958-1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Camera Design, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Care and Arrangement of Picture Collections, 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Commentary for Snider's, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Commercial Work from Way Back", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Coursework in Experimental Psychology at University of Wisconsin, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Documentary's Sliding Rules", Article for Wisconsin Film Society, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Drafts for Articles and Speeches, 1935-1958 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Experimental Book Draft, circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Lecture at Art Institute of Chicago, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Lecture at Canadian Museums Association, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Lecture, "Intuitive Photography as a Feminine Area", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Lecture at George Eastman House, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Lecture at Rochester Historical Society, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Lecture at Rochester Museum of Art, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Other Writings, 1941-1984 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Paul Vanderbilt: Selected Photographs, Exhibition Catalog, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Poems, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Poems, circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Paper on George Grosz, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - A Program for the Care of Photographs in the Library of Congress, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Proposal for a National Bibliography and Biographical Control", 1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Published Articles and Excerpts, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Speech at Bermuda Biological Station Library Dedication, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Speech, "Family of Man" Opening in Madison, Wisconsin, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Speech at Unknown Location, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Society for Photographic Education Booklet (1982, 1984) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Student Papers on Art History, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "William Henry Jackson in the East", Article in U.S. Camera Magazine, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Wisconsin Academy Review, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Wisconsin Magazine of History, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Writing on Milton Rogovin, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Writings on Photography, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1930s-1990; 4.2
    In this subseries, the author is unknown unless noted.
    - American Bicentennial Photography and Film Project, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "The Angel," by Michael Lesy, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "Memory's Eye: Paul Vanderbilt and the Iconographic Collections of the State Historical Society," by Gregory Conniff, circa 1990 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Photography-The Democratic Art," by Roy Stryker, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "No Title," by Woodie Guthrie, circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "The United States Report on National and International Biographic Problems," by Jesse H. Shera, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - About Paul Vanderbilt, by Williams College Students, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
    - "William Henry Jackson, An Anthropological Photographer in the Southwest," by Arnold R. Pilling, circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Writings on Painting and Other Arts, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Writing on William Blake, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Notes, 1887-1992; 4.3
    - 1950 Manuscript, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Access to Photo Collections, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Alphabetical List of Subjects, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Art Historians, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Article on Mythology, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Autobiography, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Barbara Crane, Book, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Barbara Crane, Found Objects, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Barbara Crane, North Portal, circa 1972 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Beauty and the Beast, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Book of Paul Vanderbilt's Photographs, 5 Chapters, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Canadian Art Bibliography, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Chicago, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Comments on H.G. Wells' The Work, Wealth and Happiness of Mankind, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Copyright, 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Current Writings, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Dunn, John, Wall Sculpture, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Exhibition Response Questionnaire, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Graphs, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Gregory Conniff, Book, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - History of an Idea, circa 1942 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Indexing, By Subject for Works of Art, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Indexing, Mechanized, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Indexing, Procedures, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Jean S. Tucker, Book, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Lecture in St. Paul, Minnesota, circa 1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Lettered Sections for Dictation, 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Magic, 1966-1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Magic Calligraphy, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Materials Indicative of Paul Vanderbilt's Thought Processes, 1980s-1992; 1887 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Note Cards, undated (Box 7, Folder 7-11)
    - Odd Notes on Bibliographic Reference, 1940s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Paul Vanderbilt's Films, 1940s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Peace, Pacifism, and Draft Resistance, 1940-1977 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Personal Notes, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Personal Theses and Beliefs, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Philosophy Index, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Photography, 1952-1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Photography, Technical, 1891-1970s (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Photo-Categories, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Photos and Plot Schemes, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Photographic Field Trip Reports, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Projected Writings, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Projection Sequences, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Raw Material Source File for Book, 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Screens, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Support for Reforms, 1970-1991 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Text of Radio Program on American Painting, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - To Libraries, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Transcription of Gibson-Marks Critique, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Travel Fellowship to Europe in 1938, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
    - Typology, General, circa 1979 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Typology, First Stage, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - University of Wisconsin Library, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Various Writing Notes, circa 1980s-1992 (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
    - Various Writing Notes, Do Not Use, 1960s-1992 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Various Writing Notes, Possible Inserts and Lists, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Various Writing Notes, Probably Omit, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Vereschagin, circa 1965 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Week Before Christmas, undated (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - World-State Projection, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - World-State Hypothetical Outline, circa 1940s (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Writing Notes for Tape, circa 1970s (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
- Diaries, 1926-1990; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Box 8
  Fourteen bound diaries and two diary fragments discuss Vanderbilt's personal and professional life. The entries dating from 1926 to 1930 are mainly introspective and of a personal nature. The diaries span several decades but contain large gaps in the dates. Also, diaries in the 1960s and 1970s may overlap.
  - Diaries, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1928-1929 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Diaries, 1956-1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1961-1965 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1966-1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1983-1987 (Box 8, Folder 10)